<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands day of joy and rejoycing, or, Long lookt for is come at last, or, The True manner of proclaiming Charls the Second King of England, &amp;c. this eighth day of this present May, to the ever honored praise of General Monck, being for the good of his country and the Parliament : to the tune of Jockey.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2955A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36556</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15724922</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15724922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104534</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104534)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1591:104)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands day of joy and rejoycing, or, Long lookt for is come at last, or, The True manner of proclaiming Charls the Second King of England, &amp;c. this eighth day of this present May, to the ever honored praise of General Monck, being for the good of his country and the Parliament : to the tune of Jockey.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Gilbertson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>With woodcuts of Charles II and his coronation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Coronations --  England --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Ballads, English.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:104534:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>
               <hi>Englands</hi> day of <unclear>Ioy</unclear> and Reioycing, Or, Long lookt for is come at laſt.</head>
            <head>Or the true manner of proclaiming CHARLS the Second King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. <date>This Eighth day of this preſent <hi>May;</hi>
               </date> to the ever honored praiſe of General <hi>Monck,</hi> being for the good of his Country, and the Parliament.</head>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>Jockey.</hi>
            </opener>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>CHear up your heart<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> kind Country-men,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, for we have them,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> déed</l>
                  <l>Be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>oſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</l>
                  <l>but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, though you have had,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> need,</l>
                  <l>For <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Foxes once were chief,</l>
                  <l>A<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> often with you laid the Thief,</l>
                  <l>But <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> he is come,</l>
                  <l>And <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> all to the run,</l>
                  <l>Though <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſo long a time have ſot,</l>
                  <l>About this and that, and I know not what,</l>
                  <l>Now General <hi>Monck</hi> hath done the thing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And proclaimd Charls our royal King.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then let us for his welfare pray,</l>
                  <l>both night and day, as on the way,</l>
                  <l>We paſſe along,</l>
                  <l>That his Enemies may be trapand,</l>
                  <l>that holds up hand, or gives command,</l>
                  <l>To do him wrong,</l>
                  <l>For there is two many now adays,</l>
                  <l>That if they might but have their ways,</l>
                  <l>Both King and Kingdome would deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>So they themſelves might it inioy,</l>
                  <l>But let all thoſe now have a care,</l>
                  <l>Leſt they fall into the hang-mans ſnare,</l>
                  <l>For it is General <hi>Monck</hi> that has done the thing</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And proclaimed,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now I will in brief declare,</l>
                  <l>therefore be ware, and you ſhall hear,</l>
                  <l>Before you go,</l>
                  <l>Though he ſo longtime hath béen croſt,</l>
                  <l>and often toſt, like to a poſt,</l>
                  <l>Both too and <unclear>throw</unclear>,</l>
                  <l>Yet now to <hi>England</hi> he muſt come,</l>
                  <l>For to redéem all thoſe from doom,</l>
                  <l>That hath béen kept under command,</l>
                  <l>And give them fréedom in the land,</l>
                  <l>And be ſure he will know all thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who are his friends, and who were his foes,</l>
                  <l>Then let his friends all merrily ſing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>that Charls is proclaim'd, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though the Foxes father did deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>with much anoy, that he might not inioy,</l>
                  <l>His own,</l>
                  <l>Now let King <hi>Charls</hi> now have his right,</l>
                  <l>both day and night, in the deſpite</l>
                  <l>Of any one,</l>
                  <l>For it would have angered any one,</l>
                  <l>For to have béen kept from their own</l>
                  <l>So long as young <hi>Charls</hi> he hath béen</l>
                  <l>This ſeaven long years durſt not be ſéen,</l>
                  <l>So was the Duke of <hi>York</hi> likewiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>But now the country people <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is General <hi>Monck</hi> has done <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>and proclaimed Charls, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Part,</head>
               <opener>To the ſame Tune.</opener>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>ANd now a Frée Parliament doth ſit,</l>
                  <l>with honour great, all men compleat,</l>
                  <l>To ſettle peace now in the land,</l>
                  <l>I pray to God they may prevail,</l>
                  <l>with fervent zeal: and not to fall,</l>
                  <l>What they have in hand,</l>
                  <l>And for to ſettle right the laws,</l>
                  <l>And to maintain the good old cauſe,</l>
                  <l>As heretofore time hath béen,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days our maiden Quéen,</l>
                  <l>For we no good laws have had,</l>
                  <l>This twenty years to make us glad,</l>
                  <l>But now General <hi>Monck</hi> has done the thing</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And proclaimed Charls our royal King.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now all the <unclear>Hanters</unclear> and the Quakers,</l>
                  <l>and the Shakers, and their Partakers,</l>
                  <l>muſt go down,</l>
                  <l>So muſt the Anabaptiſt too,</l>
                  <l>unto their <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o, no more muſt go</l>
                  <l>Aſpe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> up and down,</l>
                  <l>Though they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> houſes <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rch,</l>
                  <l>Yet now they muſt re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>air to the Church,</l>
                  <l>No more private méetings they muſt have,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet no ſpeaker them to ſave,</l>
                  <l>For they too long their wicked courſes have run</l>
                  <l>And many poor people hath almoſt undon,</l>
                  <l>But now General <hi>Monck</hi> will have no ſuch thing</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For he has proclaimd, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Quakers had the land over-run,</l>
                  <l>and it undone, if <hi>Monck</hi> had not come,</l>
                  <l>their fury to ſwage,</l>
                  <l>For when that <hi>Lambert</hi> he went forth,</l>
                  <l>unto the <hi>North,</hi> then they were in wrath,</l>
                  <l>and in great rage.</l>
                  <l>The Miniſters they would deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>If that they would not them obey,</l>
                  <l>And the Proteſtants they would have foold,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Monck</hi> their courage hath quickly cool'd,</l>
                  <l>They raiſed Armies in the <hi>Weſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For to deſtroy both man and beaſt,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Monck</hi> an alteration did bring,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And hath proclaimed, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then let us all pray to God,</l>
                  <l>with one accord, that his true word</l>
                  <l>may with us remain,</l>
                  <l>And it is a thing to be conſidered on,</l>
                  <l>and thought upon, what <hi>Monck</hi> hath done,</l>
                  <l>without deſtroying honeſt men:</l>
                  <l>To carry all thing, ſo uprightly as he hath done,</l>
                  <l>For the good of the Country ſince firſt he begun,</l>
                  <l>Without any ſhedding or ſpilling of blood,</l>
                  <l>Though he had many enemies that him withſtood,</l>
                  <l>Yet God was on his ſide, you may very wel know</l>
                  <l>That helpt him to beat down the Proteſtants foes</l>
                  <l>It is General <hi>Monck</hi> that has done this thing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And has proclaimed, &amp;e.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now you Country men all,</l>
                  <l>both great and ſmall, unto you all,</l>
                  <l>I ſend this ſong,</l>
                  <l>Hoping your taxes ſhall be fréed,</l>
                  <l>which you have much néed, and indéed</l>
                  <l>Have paid it for ſo long,</l>
                  <l>For if <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> in their ways had gone,</l>
                  <l>The poor proteſtants had béen quite undone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lambert</hi> was for the Baptiſt as I did hear,</l>
                  <l>&amp; <hi>Fleetwood</hi> for the Quakers as it doth appear,</l>
                  <l>So they two would have agréed with high renown,</l>
                  <l>That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poor Proteſtant ſhould all hade gone down</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Monck</hi> an alteration did with him bring,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And has proclaimd, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now I wiſh that all thoſe,</l>
                  <l>who are his foes, or about goes,</l>
                  <l>him to deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>That they may be ſtriken blind or lame,</l>
                  <l>unto their ſhame, that ſéeks his fame,</l>
                  <l>for to annoy.</l>
                  <l>For if brave General <hi>Monck</hi> had not ſtood our friend</l>
                  <l>For of ſorrow and woes, we ſhould never had an end</l>
                  <l>But decrit and deluſions more and more,</l>
                  <l>True loving friends they turnd out of door,</l>
                  <l>And now you kind Countrymen be not in haſt.</l>
                  <l>For though you have long lookt for it, it is come at laſt,</l>
                  <l>For General <hi>Monck</hi> has done the thing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſo God ſave Charls our royal King.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>The true manner of proclaming <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. by the too Houſes of Parliament, Lords and Commons from <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> through all the ſtreets of <hi>London,</hi> and accompanied by the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen, and Common-Counſel of the City of <hi>London,</hi> with all the City Trained-bands for their Gard, and many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Citizens on Horſe-back.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Gilbertſon,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Giltſpur-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
